Guide to the Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company records
1908-1974
WA MSS S-2704
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.34
(16 boxes) + 5 rolls
The records consist of photographs, blueprints, drawings, and reports that document the construction, maintenance, and repair of the Northwestern Pacific Railroad from Sausalito, California to Eureka, California.
Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company
The Northwestern Pacific Railroad runs between Marin and Humboldt Counties in California, much of it following the course of the South Fork of the Eel River. It was founded in the late nineteenth century as a joint venture of the Sante Fe and Southern Pacific Railroads. Portions of the railroad remain in operation in 2012.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of photographs, blueprints, drawings, and reports that document the construction, maintenance, and repair of the Northwestern Pacific Railroad from Sausalito, California to Eureka, California.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Photographs, 1931-1971. II. Drawings and Blueprints, 1908-1974. III. Other Records, 1914-1962.
Landslides -- California; Pacific railroads; Photography of railroads -- California; Railroad bridges -- California -- Design and construction; Railroad bridges -- California -- Maintenance and repair; Railroad construction workers -- California -- Pictorial works; Railroad engineers -- California; Railroad tracks -- Maintenance and repair; Railroad tunnels -- California -- Design and construction; Railroad tunnels -- California -- Maintenance and repair; Railroads -- California -- Design and construction; Railroads -- California -- Maintenance and repair; Eel River (Calif.); Humboldt County (Calif.); Marin County (Calif.); Mendocino County (Calif.); Sonoma County (Calif.); Trinity County (Calif.); Blueprints (reprographic copies) -- California -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- California -- 20th Century; Railroad engineers -- California -- 20th Century; Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company
- Photographs, 1931-1971; Series I; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of photographs (including prints and negatives) that document the construction, maintenance, and repair of the Northwestern Pacific Railroad. Many of the photographs are identified in accompanying notes or labels; some are unidentified and undated.
  - Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1939-1960 (Box 1)
  - Pepperwood and Unidentified, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Berger Creek slide, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Unidentifed, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Mile posts 173, 196, Unidentified, undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, undated; 3 (Box 1)
  - Mile post 190, Tunnel 3, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Bridge 257.84, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1948-1954 (Box 2)
  - Mile post 189 to 190.20, Ramsey, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - Mile post 193 to 194, Slides, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Mile post 168 to 171, Storm damage, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Mile post 190, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Rohnert Park Bicycle Paths, undated (Box 2)
  - Mile post 228.82, Tunnel 36, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Tunnel 39, Cave-in, 1967; 2 (Box 3)
  - Bell Springs, 1937-1961 (Box 3)
  - South Fork, Unidentified, 1931-1961 (Box 3)
  - South Fork, 1942-1956 (Box 3)
  - Nanning Creek Trestle, Unidentified, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Scotia Bluffs, 1936, undated (Box 3)
  - Tunnel 31, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Glory Hole, Tunnel 4, Unidentified, 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - Arial photographs of Tunnel 18, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Arial photographs of Tunnel 19, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Trestle Camp 9, Tunnel 26, Unidentified, 1938-1957 (Box 4)
  - Mile post 194 to 196, 1952-1954 (Box 4)
  - Mile post 167, Dos Rios, 1958-1960, undated (Box 4)
  - Mile post 187 to 189, 1943-1958, undated (Box 4)
  - Mile post 190 to 197, 1938-1958, undated (Box 4)
  - Mile post 198 to 200, Kekawaka, 1935-1958 (Box 4)
  - Mile post 240 to 248, 1948-1959, undated (Box 4)
  - South Fork, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Tunnel 16, 1930s (Box 5)
  - Scotia Bluffs, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Pepperwood, 1957? (Box 5)
  - Tunnel 26, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Tunnel 31, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified, circa 1955 (Box 5)
  - Scotia Bluffs, 1936-1958 (Box 5)
  - Island Mountain, 1956-1960 (Box 5)
  - Mile post 196, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Kekawaka Creek, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes, undated (Box 5)
  - Mile post 190, 1954 (Box 5)
- Drawings and Blueprints, 1908-1974; Series II; 3.04; (9 boxes)
  Series II consists of drawings and blueprints that document the construction, maintenance, and repair of the Northwestern Pacific Railroad.
  - Drawings, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 6)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1920-1923; 3 (Box 7)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1923-1973 (Box 8)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1965-1973 (Box 9)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1913-1966 (Box 10)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1934-1974 (Box 11)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1914-1965 (Box 12)
  - Drawings and blueprints, 1942-1973 (Box 13)
  - Right of way plats, 1908 (Box 14)
  - Right of way plats, 1908 (Box 21)
- Records, 1914-1962; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series III consists of an abstract describing deeds and ordinances relating to the Sausalito Land & Ferry Company, and reports relating to a landslide near mile post 201.
  - "Abstract of instruments affecting the county road at Waldo Point near the town of Sausalito", 1914 (Box 15)
  - Report on landslide near mile post 201, 1962; 2 (Box 15)
- Maps, Series IV; 5 rolls
  - Maps (Box 16 (Roll))
  - Maps (Box 17 (Roll))
  - Maps (Box 18 (Roll))
  - Maps (Box 19 (Roll))
  - Maps (Box 20 (Roll))